It's time for us to talk about Routing with View Router.
Okay. Routing with View Router.
Let's do this.
All right. When we take a look at a code and we look back at our CELA V app,
you can see here that we're currently faking navigation,
not actually working.
So navigation is a real thing though.
We want to actually be able to track URLs even if it is only a single-page application.
So how do we do this?
Well, again, we could always home like any developer,
but we certainly write our own solution for it.
But libraries are there to provide us some conventions,
and more importantly, make it easier for us to debug things in the future
because they provide standards for us.
So the library you're going to want to bookmark for this is View Router.
So if you go to router.viewjs.org,
this is the page you're going to need for your exercise
because one of the things I'd like you all to do going forward
is start getting more familiar with the docs
that the team has written for these libraries.
This is the official router for View.js,
so it actually is officially maintained by the team.
And so inside of here, we'll provide a lot of the explanatory code snippets and stuff.
And don't worry, we're not going to read and walk through this,
but I just want you to have this ready
so that if you have a specific question you want to read about it, it's there for you.
But what we're going to go ahead and do is let's go ahead and get that set up, shall we?
So as we can see here, I'm going to go inside of my playground
to sort of demo this first.
Let's clear out all these tabs, and if I open up, right, go here, CD Playground,
now we're good, delete that one, great, MPM Run Dev, and if we're good, we should be back.
We are back. Oh my gosh, the black though.
I need to change that so it's actually readable.
Okay, so we have this.
Let's go ahead and do some installation, shall we?
MPM Install View Router, and then the At4 specifies which version it is,
because View Router 3, unfortunately, the versions cannot line up,
3 is for View 2, 4 is for View 3.
Okay, so to verify that this has actually worked,
we can check that inside of package.json now.
You will see that, wait, this is Sella View, here's Playground.
You can see View Router right here, 4.1.6.
Okay, now that we have this,
let's go ahead and keep going.
We want to go ahead and actually get that set up.
So, the way routing works inside of
View out of the box is that what we get is the ability to define a route, right?
So, there's going to be a router controller that controls everything.
So, the way we're going to do this is we're going to create
a new file at our source called router.js.
So, router.js here,
we'll follow the syntax that we're going to see right down here.
Basically, what it allows you to do,
it allows you to define a set of routes,
that's an array that I'll explain in just a moment.
Then, what we need to be able to do then is to then take
those routes and actually apply them to the View app.
So, inside of our main.ts app,
remember here when I was saying that we can actually do things like
chain functionality on top of
this train of creating an app and mounting it.
So, this is where I typically would actually go,
const app equals create app,
because we've now created the app, app.mount app.
But then, what this allows us to do is inside of here,
we can now, we need to initialize the router from View router.
So, we get to import what?
Create View, oh, is it defined View router?
View router from View router.
Then create, there you go.
Now, the auto-complete is showing up.
Create router, because why we need the router to run everything?
So, we can say const router equals create router, just like that.
So, you can see that on this line right here,
const out, create router,
and then what you can do is then we can say app.use router.
So, let me make sure this works.
Okay, this is missing some stuff,
but I want to at least show this in its simplest form.
So, this is where I like the declarative nature of it going step by step,
in that we import what we have from the top.
We create an app that's based on
this app right here from our app.View.
Then we initialize our router,
and then the app can then use the router,
and then it's mounted to the page.
So, it's step by step,
as opposed to the alternative,
just to show you visually what that would look like,
is to then say create app.use router,
assuming you've declared it already,
dot mount app.
You can imagine once you start to chain multiple uses together,
and you're using multiple libraries,
the get-diff on that isn't very pleasant.
We want to make things easy for people to review,
and again declarative code is typically easier code to understand.
So, I prefer the multi-line approach that we have here.
Okay, but we're not quite done yet,
it's still yelling at us because
create router does take an object that we need to configure.
The first thing we need to configure are
the routes that we want to actually define for our application.
So, in other words, what URLs go to what pages?
So, right now we have all of our stuff
existing inside of this components folder,
but when we're thinking about it at a larger scale in terms of our app,
we want to think of things like pages or views.
So, the standard folder that is typically named at this point are views.
So, what you might do instead is we might actually then switch over
the Pokedex component over to the views because you can imagine
that you probably want your app to have something like
slash Pokedex will show you the Pokedex, that would make sense.
So, how would we actually define that though?
Because just because we put in the folder doesn't do much for us.
What we need to do is inside of
this router.js that you will have practice creating later,
is that we'll have this array of routes that we'll get to define.
Every route is defined by a couple of properties.
One is the desired path that you want it to be.
So, in this case, we have something for Pokedex.
Then you can define what the component is that it's going to be.
So, in this case, we want the Pokedex page component.
So, what we're going to do is we're going to import,
and this time I'm going to rename this though.
I usually prefer to try to name them like Pokedex page,
just to give it a little bit of a differentiator from the rest of the components.
So, it would be like Pokedex page from
view slash Pokedex page dot view,
and then we can just do Pokedex page.
So, we can save that. There is our routes.
Now, the only thing though is that we do need to export this const because why?
While it's being defined here,
and the reason why I like to define it over here is
because what this allows us to do is then import it.
Basically, it allows us to scope the data easier to manage.
Otherwise, your main.js file,
is going to get massively large.
So, we're going to go ahead and import routes,
I believe is what I called it.
Yep, I did call it routes.
Routes from the router.js file,
and what we can say is basically,
these are the routes that we're going to pass into it,
and that's it.
That should be good.
The other thing we need to do though,
I've realized is that we haven't defined a home page yet.
So, the app needs somewhere to go.
We have the path, this is the base route,
and then what we want to do is we want it to actually go to like a home page component.
So, we don't have that at the moment,
and that's why we find we'll just create a standard one to use real quick.
So, we'll go ahead and do that,
home page dot view.
I'm going to use my template block to really create a quick home page.
There we go.
Now, we can just import home page here at the top, and there we go.
So, here we have our routes that go to these specific components.
Any questions so far?
Feeling good? Well,
I'll keep going to this and then the questions as always are welcome.
So, these routes are being passed into here,
because the router needs to know what routes are being passed.
So, we'll save that again.
I'm not sure why some of the stuff is yelling at me.
It looks like some ESLint stuff.
So, now that we have all this stuff,
let's actually try to run it.
So, when we run it, you'll notice, okay, does this file exist?
Well, if you would go inside of Pokedex page,
it's yelling at us because, well,
the stuff we're importing now is in a completely different folder.
So, base button dot view, does this file exist?
Go back, go to components,
go to base button.
Yeah, it does exist. What are you talking about?
There we go. Refresh.
Okay. Error.
Provide a history option when calling create router.